<page><title>
Mission statement
</title>

<p> Advogato is a community site for free software developers. It also
serves as a research testbed for my research on group trust metrics
for peer certification. </p>

<p> Currently, I'm ramping up features and capabilities as fast as I
can. I want the site to serve as a nice, friendly gathering place for
all the wonderful people in our community. To that end, there's a <a
href="http://slashdot.org">Slashdot</a> style news flow with
comments. A neat feature I'm particularly proud of is a diary
server. This is a convenient place to record your notes and
observations regarding free software development, and to browse
through what others are saying. I'm hoping to add other features such
as book reviews soon. </p>

<p> While "Advogato" is a pun on the word "advocate," the goal of this
site is quite different than the usual sense of OS advocacy or free
software advocacy. Advogato's advocacy is for <i>developers</i> of
free software: to make life more enjoyable, the work more satisfying,
and to help balance the tension between the free nature of the
enterprise and the human need for tangible compensation. Advogato
doesn't care about the market share growth percent of the free
software operating systems. What Advogato cares about is how to make
the best use of the opportunities, and deal with the challenges, that
this growth is creating. </p>

<p> The other major focus of this site is a peer certification
system. The members of this site certify each other, specifying one of
three skill levels. Then, I've got a <a href="trust-metric.html">trust
metric</a> that takes the whole pile of certificates and decides a
trust level for each member. What makes the system interesting is that
it's attack resistant. If a bunch of attackers were to create lots of
accounts and mutually certify each other, only a very few would be
accepted by the trust metric, assuming there were only a few
certificates from legitimate members to the hackers. </p>

<p> A more detailed writeup of the technical details is in a <a
href="http://www.levien.com/fc.ps">draft</a> paper
submission on the topic. </p>

<p> The source code of this site is itself a free software project.
It's written as an Apache C module, using gnome-xml to store the state
of the site. It's now <a href="code.html">released</a>! </p>

<p> In summary, welcome! And please bear with the site design as I
continue to work on it. </p>

<p> <i>-- Raph Levien,</i> updated 22 Feb 2000 </p>

</page>
